Abandoned artificial satellites.
使い捨てる[つかいすてる]:to use and then throw away, 人工衛星[じんこうえいせい]:man-made satellite
（ナレーション）
使い捨てられた人工衛星
Tanks jettisoned from shuttles.
シャトル:shuttlecock, 切り離す[きりはなす]:to detach/to decapitate/to cut loose, タンク:tank (of liquid)
シャトルが切り離したタンク
Refuse generated during
space station construction.
ステーション:station, 建造[けんぞう]:building/construction, 廃棄物[はいきぶつ]:waste matter/waste/garbage
ステーション建造時に出た廃棄物
This vast amount of junk floating in space,
space debris, is a very serious threat.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 浮かぶ[うかぶ]:to float|to rise to surface|to come to mind, たくさん:a lot/lots|enough
宇宙に浮かぶ たくさんのゴミ
スペース:space (room, area, outer space), デブリ:debris, 実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being
スペースデブリは
実は とても危険な存在です
This is a story of 2075, a time in which
this space garbage has become a problem.
2075年―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|, 物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend
これは 宇宙のゴミが
問題になった時代の物語
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
（ギガルト）
新入り お前はそこで待ってろ
Okay, rookie,
you stay put there.
Are you listening
to me, rookie?
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be, 新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
聞こえないのか？ 新入り
（ハチマキ）あっ…
Wait there. Don't go near
the engine until...
エンジン:engine, 近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with
（ギガルト）そこで待ってろ
エンジンに近づくのは…
Hey! Rookie!
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
こら 新入り！
Did you hear a word I said?!
勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess
何 勘違いしてんだ おい！
Hey!
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation), 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person, 信号[しんごう]:signal/signalling|traffic light, ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
何やってんだ ったく…
停止信号ぐらい知っとけ
What do you think
you're doing, damn it?
At least learn your suit's
halt code!
（ハチマキ）あっ…
Stay calm. Just swing
to the right.
落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||, ライト:light, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 振る[ふる]:to wave|to sprinkle|to cast (actor)||, 振る[ぶる]:assuming the air of .../behaving like ...|to put on airs
（ギガルト）
落ち着け ライトに体を振ればいい
ああっ…
無駄[むだ]:futility/uselessness/pointlessness, 慌てる[あわてる]:to become confused (disconcerted, disorganized, disorganised)/to be flustered|to be in a hurry, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
（ギガルト）ええい
無駄に慌てやがって この野郎
You panicked over nothing,
you little bastard...
エンジン:engine, 制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking, 計[けい]:plan|meter|(in) total, 計[はか]:progress, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
（ギガルト）くそ！
エンジンと制御計が生きてやがった
Crap, the engine and control
system were still working!
♪～
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
Phase 2
Like a Dream
（ハチマキたち）
ウッ ウッ ウッ ウッ…
ア～ ウッ！
（テレビ音声）どうした～ ウッ！
Six!
（ラビィ）６！
（ハチマキ）来た来た… 来たー！
ナンバー:number
（テレビ音声）
６が来ました ナンバー６
And our next number is a six!
Yes! Yes! Yes! Yes! Yes!!!
Banzai! Banzai!
万歳[まんざい]:door-to-door comedic duo, 万歳[ばんざい, ばんぜい]:crying "banzai" (or raising one's hands in the banzai gesture)|something worthy of celebration|giving up||
万歳！ 万歳！
（ラビィ）
やったー やった やった
Huh? Did something happen?
（タナベ）
あっ… 何かあったんですか？
宝くじ[たからくじ, たからクジ]:lottery, 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||
（ハチマキ）
宝くじが当たったんだよ
I won the lottery,
that's what!
Yep! 300 million!
億[おく]:10^8/100,000,000/hundred million
そう ３億！
300 million?!
億[おく]:10^8/100,000,000/hundred million
３億！？
Not just yet.
（ユーリ）まだですよ
（タナベ）え？
But if the next number is a 4, he wins.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 億[おく]:10^8/100,000,000/hundred million
（ユーリ）
でも 次に４が出たら３億です
No way!
うそ！
I'm the one who bought
the ticket, Hachi,
買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
ねえねえねえ ハチ
買ってきたのは私だからさ―
...so if you win, I get half!
No, no a quarter is fine!
当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||, 半分[はんぶん]:half, 半分[はんぷん]:half minute
当たったら半分…
いや ４分の１でいい
I helped out with the luck dance,
so I get some too, right?
祈る[いのる]:to pray/to wish, 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
（課長）僕も
お祈り手伝ってたんだから―
もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
もらえるよね ねえ？
Um...
格好[かっこう, かっこ]:shape|appearance|state||
あの… ど… どうして
そんな格好なんですか？
W-Why are you
dressed like that?
Wanna join in?
（フィー）あんたもやる？
（タナベ）えっ
They say it's a good-luck charm
that's a sure thing.
当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||, まじない:charm/incantation/spell
（フィー）
よく当たるまじないなんだってさ
で… でも
But I...
Hey, here comes
the last number!
ラストナンバー:last/end/conclusion, ラストナンバー:number
（ハチマキ）
おい ラストナンバーだ
えっ あっ…
（ハチマキたち）
ウッ ウッ ウッ ウッ ウッ…
ア～ ウッ！
Oo.
C'mon, four!
４ 来い！
（課長）４！
Four!
４！
（タナベ）４！
Four!
４！
（一同）ぬあーっ…
And those are
tonight's numbers!
（テレビ音声）こんなん出ました
Aw, man...
連敗[れんぱい]:consecutive defeats/series of defeats, かする:to change into/to convert into/to transform, かする:to inflict/to impose (a fine, etc.), やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
（ハチマキ）あーあ 172連敗
かすりもしやがらねえ くそ
172 straight losses.
And partial matches don't
pay anything, either, damn it...
I suppose that half-hearted dance
just won't do the trick.
やはり:too/also|still, インチキ:cheating/fraud/trickery, 踊り[おどり]:dance, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（ユーリ）やはり
インチキな踊りでは駄目ですね
If you're serious, you should go all-out.
This is supposed to be quite effective.
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 本格的[ほんかくてき]:genuine|full-scale|full-fledged
やるなら もっと本格的に
なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, かなり:considerably/fairly/quite, 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||
これなんか
かなり当たるようですよ
Good idea! Do you want
to try that next time?
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order
（課長）
いいね 次 それでやろうか
In that case, please be the
human sacrifice, Chief.
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, いけにえ:sacrifice (to the gods)|victim/scapegoat, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, いたす:to do
（ユーリ）ああ それでは課長は
いけにえを お願いいたします
Don't make jokes
like that!
冗談[じょうだん, ぎだん]:jest/joke/funny story, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, ちょうだい:receiving/reception|eating, ちょうだい:very long/great length
（課長）
なっ 冗談は やめてちょうだいよ
Senpai, why are you
playing the lottery?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 宝くじ[たからくじ, たからクジ]:lottery, 当てる[あてる]:to hit|to expose|to apply (e.g. patch)||
先輩
宝くじ当てて どうするんですか？
Lay off... It's none
of your concern.
関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
うるせえ お前には関係ない
This bozo's dream
is to buy a spaceship.
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, 夢[ゆめ]:dream
こいつ 宇宙船 買うのが夢なのよ
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, ムチャクチャ:nonsensical/unreasonable/absurd, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive
えっ で… でも 宇宙船って
ムチャクチャ高いんじゃ…
B-But aren't spaceships really,
really expensive?
That's why he's playing the lottery!
宝くじ[たからくじ, たからクジ]:lottery
だから 宝くじ やってんじゃない
あっ そーだ
Hey, that reminds me!
Let me show you
something cool. This is...
見せる[みせる]:to show/to display
いいもん見してやるよ これね…
（ハチマキ）ああっ
What's the problem?
You showed it to us before!
見せる[みせる]:to show/to display
（フィー）何だよ
前は見せてくれただろ？
Yeah, so don't go showing it
without asking!
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 見せる[みせる]:to show/to display
だからって 勝手に見せんなよ
What is it?
何なんですか？ それ
"Idea Notebook for Acquiring
a Spaceship of My Own."
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 獲得[かくとく]:acquisition/possession, 構想[こうそう]:plan/plot/idea, ノート:notebook/copy-book/exercise book
（ユーリ）
マイ宇宙船 獲得構想ノート
はい？
What?
Hoshino-san filled it with ways
he could get a spaceship.
（ユーリ）星野(ほしの)さんが―
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner, 書きためる[かきためる]:to accumulate one's unpublished paintings or writings
宇宙船を手に入れるための方法を
書きためたものです
Apparently, he had it even before
he joined the company.
入社[にゅうしゃ]:joining a company/getting a job with a company/entering a company, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（フィー）
入社する前から 持ってたらしいよ
（タナベ）へえ
But Senpai, it's not easy
to win the lottery...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 宝くじ[たからくじ, たからクジ]:lottery, 簡単[かんたん]:simple/easy|brief, 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||
でも 先輩 宝くじって
簡単には当たらないんじゃ
ぐっ… く…
There's lots of different ways.
方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner, いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), 社長[しゃちょう]:company president/manager/director, 賞[しょう]:prize/award, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
方法は いろいろあんだよ
社長賞をもらうとかさ
I could get the President's Prize, for instance.
Come on, it's not like you'd
ever be chosen for that.
選ぶ[えらぶ]:to choose/to select
あのな～
お前が選ばれるわけないだろう？
He's right, Hachi. Besides, the President's
Prize is a life-sized Nora-kun.
そうだよ ハッちゃん
社長[しゃちょう]:company president/manager/director, 賞[しょう]:prize/award, 等身大[とうしんだい]:life-size/life-sized
それに 社長賞って
等身大ノーラ君なんだから
ノ…
I-I could also rescue some rich old
geezer who's about to kick the bucket,
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters)
ほ… 他にも―
お迎え[おむかえ]:receiving/welcoming|final call, 大富豪[だいふごう]:multi-millionaire/extremely rich person|Japanese card game, 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
お迎えが来そうな
大富豪のじいさんを助けるとか―
...or marry some
rich old lady, or...
逆玉[ぎゃくたま]:man who marries a wealthy or upwardly-mobile woman/(male) gold digger
逆玉とか…
Are you the
life-saving type?
人助け[ひとだすけ]:act of mercy/helping another person, 柄[え]:handle/grip|stalk (of a mushroom, leaf, etc.), 柄[がら]:pattern|body build|essential qualities|
人助けって柄？
And marrying rich?
Would anybody ever marry you?
逆玉[ぎゃくたま]:man who marries a wealthy or upwardly-mobile woman/(male) gold digger, そもそも:in the first place/to begin with|... the heck (e.g. "what the heck?"), 結婚[けっこん]:marriage
逆玉っていうか
そもそも結婚できるんですか？
気になる[きになる]:to be on one's mind|to feel like|to fancy, 結婚[けっこん]:marriage, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship
くっ… 人間その気になりゃあ
結婚だろうが 宇宙船だろうがよ
If a man puts his mind to it, he can get married
or even buy a spaceship!
So, what else do you have written in there?
Let me see your notebook.
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
…で 他には
何が書いてあるんです？
見せる[みせる]:to show/to display, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one, ノート:notebook/copy-book/exercise book
見せてくださいよ そのノート
What are you doing here, anyway?!
It's your day off, isn't it?!
非番[ひばん]:off duty
お前 何しに来たんだ？
非番だろ？
あっ そうなんですよ
That's right, it is!
You know the
procedure, right?
手順[てじゅん]:process/procedure/sequence
（ハチマキ）
手順は分かってるよな？
Right. I learned how
in a workshop.
研修[けんしゅう]:training (esp. in-service)/induction course, 習う[ならう]:to take lessons in/to be taught/to learn (from a teacher)
（タナベ）
はい 研修で習いましたから
Okay, try to
back away.
下がる[さがる]:to come down|to hang|to move back||
おーし 下がってみろ
Right.
（タナベ）はい
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
うわあ うわあ…
（ハチマキ）バカ野郎
You moron, you're spinning because you're not
thrusting through your body's center of gravity.
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 中心[ちゅうしん]:center/centre|-centered, 中心[なかご]:core|tang (of a sword, etc.)|middle of a nest of boxes, 射抜く[いぬく]:to shoot through something (wall, body, etc.)/to pierce (e.g. with an arrow or a look), 回る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|, 回る[まわる]:to turn|to visit several places|to function well|
ちゃんと体の中心を射抜かないから
回っちまうんだよ
I'm sorry...!
（タナベ）うっ すいません
You gotta be able to judge something's
center of mass in an instant.
質量[しつりょう]:mass, 中心[ちゅうしん]:center/centre|-centered, 中心[なかご]:core|tang (of a sword, etc.)|middle of a nest of boxes, 瞬時[しゅんじ]:moment/instant, 判断[はんだん]:judgment|divination|judgement
質量の中心を
瞬時に判断できるようになれ
'Cause when you're holding tools or debris, it's
even harder to determine your center of mass.
仕事中[しごとちゅう]:at work/in the midst of work/working, 道具[どうぐ]:tool/implement|means, デブリ:debris, 抱える[かかえる]:to hold or carry under or in the arms|to have (esp. problems, debts, etc.)|to employ
仕事中は
道具やデブリを抱えて―
重心[じゅうしん]:centre of gravity (center)|centroid|(one's) balance, もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, づらい:difficult to .../hard to ...
重心は
もっと分かりづらくなるんだからな
Y-Yes, sir!
という:called/named|as many as, 止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
ああっ はい
…というか 止めてくださいよ
Or more to the point,
please stop me!
Of course.
（チェンシン）はい
（タナベ）うっ…
うう…
す…すいません
T-Thank you.
Not at all.
いたす:to do
（チェンシン）どういたしまして
Just think of your center of gravity as
somewhere around the pit of your stomach.
重心[じゅうしん]:centre of gravity (center)|centroid|(one's) balance, 位置[いち]:place/situation/position, みぞおち:pit of the stomach/solar plexus|place where water falls, 辺り[あたり, ほとり]:on the bank of|(in the) neighbourhood|around (Sunday, last year, etc...)|, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
重心位置は みぞおち辺りだって
考えておくといいよ
Long time now see,
Cheng-Shin.
久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you)
（ハチマキ）
久しぶりだな チェンシン
Good to be back, Hachimaki.
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently, ハチマキ:headband, ようやく:finally/at last|barely, ようやく:summary/digest, 新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh
ただいま ハチマキ
ようやく入ったんだね 新しい人
I see you've finally got
yourselves a new recruit.
Is he a friend
of yours?
知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance
お知り合いですか？
Cheng-Shin and I were hired at the same time.
He works as a pilot in Aerospace Section.
同期[どうき]:same period|same year (of graduation, entering a company, etc.)|synchronization, 入社[にゅうしゃ]:joining a company/getting a job with a company/entering a company, 航宙[こうちゅう]:space flight, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), パイロット:pilot
同期入社のチェンシン
航宙課でパイロットやってる
My wings are still clipped, though. I'm not
allowed to carry anything but cargo.
貨物[かもつ, かぶつ]:cargo/freight|money or assets, やらす:to allow/to let (somebody) do/to make (somebody) do, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me), 半人前[はんにんまえ]:half share|half a man
まだ 貨物しかやらしてもらえない
半人前だけどね
It will be 1800 hours momentarily.
ISPV-7 is about to enter nighttime mode,
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room
（アナウンス）間もなく18時です
夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights
ISPV-７は
夜時間に入りますので―
...so we ask that all corporate blocks
switch over to internal power sources.
各[かく]:each/every/all, 各[おのおの]:each|you (plural), ブロック:to block (e.g. the way), 電源[でんげん]:source of electricity/electrical power|power (button on TV, etc.), 切り替え[きりかえ]:exchange/conversion/replacement, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
各企業ブロックは
電源切り替えをお願いします
Good for you, you have
a new partner.
待望[たいぼう]:waiting expectantly/waiting eagerly|long-awaited, 新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards)
（チェンシン）よかったじゃないか
待望の新人さんが入って
Too bad she doesn't have
a lick of talent.
才能[さいのう]:talent/ability, かけら:fragment/broken piece|ounce (of truth, conscience, etc.)
才能のかけらもねえがな
Isn't everyone like that
at first?
初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25)
初めてなら あんなもんだろ？
Besides, she's cute.
一生懸命[いっしょうけんめい]:very hard/with utmost effort/with all one's might
それに かわいい子じゃないか
一生懸命で
I like her enthusiasm.
Girls like that oughta be
secretaries or something.
秘書[ひしょ]:(private) secretary|treasured book/secret book
そういうのは
秘書とか やってりゃいいんだ
Oh, so we agree
that she's cute, then.
部分[ぶぶん]:portion/section/part, 同意[どうい]:agreement/consent|same meaning
おっ かわいいって部分には
同意なんだ
You'll never cut it as a pilot.
Your eyes are terrible.
パイロット:pilot, 失格[しっかく]:disqualification/elimination/incapacity (legal), 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
お前 パイロット失格だな
目が悪い
You can't admit it,
can you?
素直[すなお]:obedient/meek|honest
素直じゃないな
Lay off.
うっせえ
Hey, Hachimaki!
ハチマキ:headband, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
（キース）よう ハチマキ
宇宙船は買えたか？
You buy your spaceship yet?
I hear the Yankees lost.
That makes our records the same.
負ける[まける]:to lose|to succumb|to be inferior to||, 同率[どうりつ]:the same ratio or percentage, 首位[しゅい]:first place/head position/leading position
ヤンキース 負けたってよ
これで同率首位だ
Oh, so I guess you lost
the lottery, huh?
やっぱり:too/also|still, 外れる[はずれる]:to be disconnected/to get out of place/to be off, 宝くじ[たからくじ, たからクジ]:lottery
何だ やっぱり外れたのか 宝くじ
Even if I do get a spaceship someday,
I'm never letting you aboard it, you hear me?
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure, 絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
宇宙船を手に入れても お前だけは
絶対 乗せてやんねえからな
アハハ:a-ha-ha (laughing loudly), 冗談[じょうだん, ぎだん]:jest/joke/funny story
アハハ 冗談
I'm kidding.
But I will!
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, 貸す[かす]:to lend/to loan|to rent out
（バクティ）俺は乗るぞ
だから ちょっとだけ貸してくれよ
So will you lend me some money?
Playing the ponies again?
競馬[けいば]:horse racing, 競馬[くらべうま]:traditional horse-racing/originally two horses head-to-head or ten at a time, esp. May 5th event at Kamigamo shrine
また競馬か？
No way! I found a sure thing
in the dog races!
ドッグレース:dog racing
いやあ ドッグレースで
いいのがあってさあ
Hey, what's it gonna be?!
I'm taking the last bets now!
締め切る[しめきる]:to close up/to shut up (e.g. behind doors)|to cut off (e.g. because a deadline has expired)
（トモルド）おい どうすんだ？
もう締め切るぞ
Give me a minute!
（バクティ）ちょっと待ってよ
C'mon! Somebody!
Anybody!
（デボン）なあ 誰か 誰か…
Work the night shift for me!
I have a date!
夜勤[やきん]:night shift, 代わる[かわる]:to succeed|to take the place of|to be exchanged, デート:date/go on a date, 約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny
誰か 夜勤 代わってくれよ
デートの約束が
You're just gonna get
dumped again, anyway.
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best
どうせ またフラれるんだろ？
Lend me some money,
and I'll do whatever you want!
金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal, 貸す[かす]:to lend/to loan|to rent out
（バクティ）
金 貸してくれたら 何でもするぞ
Pipe down back there.
黙る[だまる]:to be silent
お前は黙ってろ
皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything
（ババイヤン）
はーい やもめ男の皆さーん
Step right up,
my widower friends!
I've got some
new goodies!
新作[しんさく]:new work/new production
新作が入りましたよ
Rent or buy,
but cash only, please!
レンタル:rental, 買い取る[かいとる]:to buy/to purchase, 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 現金[げんきん]:cash/ready money|mercenary, どうぞ:please/kindly|by all means
レンタル 買い取り
全て 現金でどうぞ
Save some for me!
取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
俺の分 取っとけよ 俺の分
I'm not taking
any more bets!
締め切る[しめきる]:to close up/to shut up (e.g. behind doors)|to cut off (e.g. because a deadline has expired)
（トモルド）こっち 締め切るぞ！
Wait, I want in, too!
Hey, Cheng-Shin! Spot me!
待て待て 俺も入る
貸す[かす]:to lend/to loan|to rent out
おい チェンシン ちょっと貸せ
（チェンシン）はあ？
C'mon, it's a sure thing!
I'll pay you back triple!
倍[ばい]:twice/double|times, 返し[かえし]:reversal|return gift|barb (on a fishing hook)|, してやる:to do for (someone)
大丈夫だって
３倍返しにしてやるから
♪～
（ハチマキ）おっ
I did it!
できた！
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩 できました！
Senpai, I did it!
Don't get cocky just 'cause
you did it once.
回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 喜ぶ[よろこぶ]:to be delighted|to congratulate|to gratefully accept
１回できたくらいで喜ぶな
もう１回
Again!
Right!
はい
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
やった またできた
先輩 できましたよ！
I did it!
I did it again!
Senpai, I did it!
Geez...
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation), 当たり前[あたりまえ]:natural/reasonable|usual
ったく… できて当たり前(めえ)だって
Of course you did.
I've been working with you
for days, haven't I?
何日[なんにち]:what day|how many days, つきあわせる:to place persons opposite/to come face to face with|to compare (with)
何日 つきあわせたんだよ
あっ
I knew you could do it,
Cheng-Shin!
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger
（バクティ）
さすがだよな チェンシンは
He's had great grades
ever since training!
研修[けんしゅう]:training (esp. in-service)/induction course, 成績[せいせき]:results/record/grades, 良い[よい]:good|sufficient (can be used to turn down an offer)|profitable (e.g. deal, business offer, etc.)|
（デボン）研修の時から
成績 良かったよなあ
Hey, what's the occasion?
盛り上がる[もりあがる]:to swell/to rise|to rouse
（ハチマキ）
よう 盛り上がってるじゃねえか
Cheng-Shin says he's
moved up in the world.
出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career
チェンシンが出世したんだってよ
Moved up?
出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career
出世？
He's a ship's captain.
船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman
（トモルド）船長さまだよ
I said I'm a copilot.
副操縦士[ふくそうじゅうし]:copilot
副操縦士だって
They're finally letting me
carry people.
ようやく:finally/at last|barely, ようやく:summary/digest, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||, 飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump
ようやく 人を乗せて
飛べるようになったんだ
They are?
そっか
Okay! Let's have a toast!
To the future captain!
乾杯[かんぱい]:toast|drinking one's glass dry|cheers, 未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come, 船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman
よし 乾杯しようぜ！
未来の船長に
ビール:beer, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
（社員）あっ じゃ
ビール頼みましょうか？
I'll go order
some beer, then!
This is Cheng-Shin we're talking about,
so get us some Shaoxing wine!
祝い[いわい, ゆわい]:congratulation/congratulations/celebration, 紹興酒[しょうこうしゅ, シャオシンチュウ]:shaoxingjiu (Chinese alcohol made from rice or glutinous millet)
（ハチマキ）チェンシンの
祝いなんだから 紹興酒だろ
Um, I don't usually drink that...
That was fast...
Just three years.
早[はや]:already/now/by this time, 早[はよ]:early
早(はえ)えな ３年か
You tryin' to move straight up
to company president?
一気[いっき]:chug!/drink! (said repeatedly as a party cheer), 社長[しゃちょう]:company president/manager/director, 目指す[めざす]:to aim at/to have an eye on|to go toward
このまま一気に
社長でも目指すか？
Not really.
木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 往還[おうかん]:traffic/coming and going/highway, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman
ならないよ
僕は木星往還船の船長になるんだ
I want to be
the captain of a ship to Jupiter.
You've been sayin' that for years.
Is Jupiter all that great?
木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 魅力的[みりょくてき]:charming/fascinating/attractive
前から言ってたな
そんなに木星が魅力的か？
Yes, you're so great,
Cecille baby!
魅力的[みりょくてき]:charming/fascinating/attractive, いとしい:lovely/dear/beloved
ジョーン 魅力的！
いとしのジョーン…
When do you
start flying?
飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump
いつからなんだ？ 飛ぶの
A week from now,
on the GO-S27.
週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of), 後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|
１週間後の GOS-27
No kiddin'...
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
そっか 頑張れよ
Well, give it all you got.
I hope you get a spaceship
soon, too, Hachi.
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 手に入る[てにはいる]:to obtain/to come into possession of/to get hold of
ハチも
早く 宇宙船が手に入るといいな
Y-Yeah, Me, too.
おっ おお そうだな
ハァ…
あっ…
Ship's captain, huh...?
船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman
船長か…
Um...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, つきあわせる:to place persons opposite/to come face to face with|to compare (with)
（タナベ）あの… 先輩
つきあわせちゃって すいません
I'm sorry for dragging you
out here with me, Senpai.
I'll practice on my
own from now on.
練習[れんしゅう]:practice/practising
あとは１人で練習しますから
Huh?
んあ？
Um... The thing is, I think
I can handle it by myself.
（タナベ）
あの… だから １人でも…
Hachimaki!
（キース）ハチマキー
（ハチマキ）あっ
Vega uses that area after 1400 hours, so if
you're gonna keep going, use cargo bay B4.
社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc.
（キース）ここは
14時から ベガ社が使うからな
続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on, 倉庫[そうこ]:storehouse/warehouse/godown
続けるなら Ｄ４倉庫にしとけ
Hey, is that him? The idiot who says
he's gonna buy his own ship?
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
（社員１）おい あいつか？
宇宙船 買うってバカは
Buy a spaceship? Do they get
that kinda pay in Half Section?
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
（社員２）宇宙船を買う？
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 給料[きゅうりょう]:salary/wages
半課って
そんなに給料 よかったっけ？
Do they get double the pay
'cause they've only got half the people?
人数[にんずう, ひとかず]:the number of people|many people/a large number of people, 半分[はんぶん]:half, 半分[はんぷん]:half minute, 給料[きゅうりょう]:salary/wages, 倍[ばい]:twice/double|times
人数半分だから
給料は倍だってか？
笑い声[わらいごえ]:laughter
（３人の笑い声）
Is something funny,
you bastards?
おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
何か おかしいかよ？
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, ハチマキ:headband
（社員１）あ？
（キース）おい ハチマキ
Hey, Hachimaki...
Is me buying a spaceship
that funny?
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
（ハチマキ）俺が
宇宙船 買ったら おかしいか？
- Um, senpai...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
あの… 先輩
（ハチマキ）
なんとか言ってみろ こら
C'mon, say something!
おかしい:funny/amusing|strange, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
おかしいに決まってんだろ
Of course it's funny! It's funny to hear a punk
from Half Section deluding himself with dreams.
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 夢[ゆめ]:dream
半課のガキが
夢みてえなこと言ってんなよ
くっ…
あっ おい あっ…
Hey!
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（社員１）うっ…
（ハチマキ）夢で悪いか！
What's wrong
with dreams?!
What're you doing, Senpai?
Why are you fighting?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
何やってんですか 先輩！
ケンカ:quarrel/brawl/fight, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
ケンカなんて ええっ！？
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation
（社員３）このガキ！
You punk!
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation
（ハチマキ）ううっ…
（社員３）おっ…
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation
（社員２）ううっ おおっ…
（社員１）ううっ…
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）あっ 先輩！
Senpai!
I've got you now,
you Half Section bastard!
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（社員２）捕まえたぞ 半課野郎
You messed with
the wrong people.
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, ふざける:to joke/to jest|to make fun of, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action, 食らう[くらう]:to eat/to drink|to receive (e.g. a blow)
（社員１）
ふざけやがって 食らえ！
Eat this!
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation
（ハチマキ）わあっ…
（社員１）おらおら どうした？
Not so tough now, are ya?!
（ハチマキ）うわっ うっ うわっ…
（ハチマキ）うわあっ ああ…
ああっ… あっ あっ…
うう うう… あっ あっ…
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
うわああーっ
Hey, are you okay?
（ギガルト）おい 大丈夫か？
Pull it together, rookie.
You want a spaceship, right?
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built), 新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
（ギガルト）
しっかりしろよ 新入り
お前 宇宙船 欲しいんだろ？
Don't rush things.
You can take your time.
焦る[あせる]:to be in a hurry/to be impatient/to be flustered, ゆっくり:slowly/at ease/restful
焦んなよ ゆっくりでいい
ゆっくり ゆっくりだ
Take your time.
Take your time...
あっ… うっ…
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation)
ハァ… ったくよ
Damn it...
Sounds like you've come around.
意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（ユーリ）
意識が戻ったみたいですね
具合[ぐあい]:condition/state/manner
（ユーリ）具合 どうですか？
How do you feel?
Huh? Fine...
（ハチマキ）あっ… ああ
You were moaning in your
sleep pretty badly.
ひどい:cruel/heartless|violent
何か ひどく
うなされてましたが…
It was an old dream.
I was having a bad dream.
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant
昔の夢だよ 嫌な夢 見ちまった
I see. Well, I'm glad
it was just a dream.
夢[ゆめ]:dream
（ユーリ）そうですか
夢でよかったですね
何だ？ これ
What the heck
is this?
Oh. Miss Tanabe left some
medicine with me.
薬[くすり]:medicine|efficacious chemical (gunpowder, pesticide, etc.)|(pottery) glaze|, 薬[やく]:dope/narcotics|medication
ああ タナベさんから薬を
（ハチマキ）あっそ
No kiddin'.
She was very worried
about you.
とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
彼女 とても心配してましたよ
She wouldn't listen to me. She said she'd sit up
with you because she was responsible.
原因[げんいん]:cause/origin/source, 看病[かんびょう]:nursing (a patient)
自分が原因だから
看病するって聞かないんです
I sent her away because this
is the men's dorm, though.
男子[だんし]:youth/young man, 寮[りょう]:hostel/dormitory|bureau (government department beneath a ministry under the ritsuryo system), 寮[つかさ]:office|chief|(Yaeyama Islands in Okinawa) person (usually a woman) whose duty it is to officiate at religions ceremonies, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
ここは男子寮だから
帰らせましたけどね
フン
Who asked her
to butt in?
余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly
余計なことを
すげえ:incredible/unbelievable
チェンシン お前はすげえな
Cheng-Shin,
you're amazing.
I...
俺は…
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
（ハチマキ）
俺は何やってんだろうな 一体
What the hell am I doing
with my life?
（フィー）DBR 0721414
DBR-0720-1414.
As bad luck would have it,
this bird has propellant left in it.
やっかい:trouble/burden|care, やっかい:translating and explaining, 推進剤[すいしんざい]:propellant, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
こいつ やっかいなことに
推進剤が残ってるのよね
It started out as an asteroid probe,
so it has excellent evasive capability.
もともと:originally/by nature/from the start, 小惑星[しょうわくせい]:asteroid, 探査機[たんさき]:(space) probe
もともと
小惑星の探査機だったから―
回避[かいひ]:evasion/avoidance, 能力[のうりょく]:ability/faculty, 能力[のうりき]:low-ranking priest who does manual labour at a temple/male temple employee, ずばぬける:to tower above the rest/to be by far the best/to be prominent
回避能力は ずばぬけているし―
And its orbit is retrograde to ours, so even
making a rendezvous is going to be tricky.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 逆行[ぎゃっこう, ぎゃくこう]:reverse movement/retrogression|retrogradation, ランデブー:meeting/rendez-vous, 難しい[むずかしい, むつかしい]:difficult|fussy|gloomy||
軌道が逆行しているから
ランデブーも難しいのよ
Our section tried to recover it
three years ago,
回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
３年前に うちで
回収しようとしたんだけど―
作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 噴射[ふんしゃ]:jet/spray/injection, 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from), 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
作業ミスで
噴射が始まって逃げられちゃった
...but an accident caused it thrusters
to fire up, and it got away from us.
Of course, every other company's
attempts have failed so far, too.
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder
まっ よその会社も
今まで 全部 失敗してんだけどね
Wow, this sounds like
it'll be tricky.
ややこしい:puzzling/tangled/complicated
へえ ややこしそうですね
Well, we would've preferred to leave it alone, but it's come
into low Earth orbit and has intersected our work orbit.
放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
まあ 放っておいても
よかったんだけど―
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 降りる[おりる]:to descend (e.g. a mountain)|to alight (e.g. from bus)|to step down||, 営業[えいぎょう]:business/trade/sales, 重なる[かさなる]:to be piled up|to come one after another|to overlap (each other), 重なる[おもなる]:main/principal/important
低軌道に降りてきて
うちの営業軌道と重なっちゃってさ
Luckily, it hasn't made any
orbital corrections near Earth.
幸い[さいわい]:happiness/blessedness|luckily, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 変更[へんこう]:change/modification/alteration
幸い地球の近くでは
一度も軌道変更…
Hachi!
コピー:copy/photocopy
ハチ ユー コピー？
You copy?
ああ
Yeah...
It's the same as
any other run, right?
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
どうせ いつもと同じだろ
Hachi!
You better shape up!
なさる:to do
ハチ！ シャキッとしなさい
Starting today, I'm having Tanabe
participate directly in our missions.
ミッション:mission, 直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal, 加わる[くわわる]:to be added to|to join in (e.g. a group of friends)|to increase (e.g. heat)|, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
今日からタナベにも ミッションに
直接 加わってもらうんだから―
Set a good example
as her senpai.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 手本[てほん]:copybook|model/pattern, 見せる[みせる]:to show/to display
先輩として 手本を見せな
She's right!
そうですよ
Show me how
it's done, Senpai!
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
お願いします 先輩
Hachi, try not to butt heads with other
companies' departments, all right?
あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 部署[ぶしょ]:one's post/one's station/department, ぶつかる:to strike against/to collide with|to encounter
ハチ あんまり
よその部署とぶつかるなよ
It makes trouble for me...
立場[たちば]:standpoint/position/situation, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
私の立場…
（ハチマキ）悪かったよ
- Yeah, sorry about that.
Hey, wait a minute!
（ラビィ）あっ ちょっと待って
ジャーン:clash/bang
ダラララララ… ジャーン！
Ta-dah!
Number A-7777-777!
組[くみ]:set (of items)|group (of people)|typesetting, 番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint
Ａ組 7777-777番
You can tell it's a lucky number just
by looking! With this baby, we...
ラッキー:lucky, ナンバー:number
見るからにラッキーナンバーだろ？
これなら…
Thanks,
but no thanks.
俺は いいよ
（ラビィ）えっ…
I'm done with
lotto drawings.
宝くじ[たからくじ, たからクジ]:lottery
宝くじは もういいんだ
（ラビィ）いいって…
"Done"?
H-Hey, Hachimaki! Make sure you pay me back!
I bought this for you!
ハチマキ:headband
お… おい ハチマキ！
金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal, ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 払う[はらう]:to pay (e.g. money, bill)|to brush off|to drive away (e.g. one's competitors)||, 立て替える[たてかえる]:to pay an advance/to put down money on something|to pay for another
金はちゃんと払えよ
私が立て替えたんだから！
And for these
apology candies, too!
菓子[かし]:pastry/confectionery, 代[しろ]:substitution|material|price||, 代[よ]:world/society/age
あと このおわびの菓子代！
Um, Senpai...?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）あの… 先輩
I'm no good at EVA work,
but I'm pretty lucky.
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 運[うん]:fortune/luck
私 ＥＶＡは駄目ですけど
運はいいんです
That's what got me into the company.
And a space assignment, too.
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
だから
この会社にも入れちゃったし―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 勤務[きんむ]:service/duty/work
宇宙勤務だって…
If it's okay with you, why don't we
go buy a lotto ticket together?
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 買い[かい]:buying|buyer|purchase, 宝くじ[たからくじ, たからクジ]:lottery
よかったら 一緒に
買いに行きませんか？ 宝くじ
Who knows,
maybe we'll win?
ひょっと:possibly/perhaps|unintentionally, 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
ひょっとしたら
当たるかもしれませんよ
Show some spirit, Senpai!
気合い[きあい]:scream/yell/fighting spirit, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
気合い入れてくださいよ 先輩
Is that hachimaki headband
just for show?
ハチマキ:headband, 飾り[かざり]:decoration
このハチマキは飾りですか？
I might be a useless rookie,
but I don't sulk about it!
そりゃあ:very/extremely|that is, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful, ひよっこ:young bird/chick|hina doll, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
そりゃあ 私は 使えない
ひよっこかもしれないけど―
ふてくされる:to become sulky/to become irresponsible (due to disgruntlement), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
だからって ふてくされるなんて
I thought you said you were gonna work
hard until you had your own spaceship!
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
マイ宇宙船 手に入れるまで
頑張るって言ったじゃないですか
Isn't getting a spaceship
your dream, Senpai?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship
先輩の夢なんでしょ？ 宇宙船
かげん:(moon's) last quarter, かげん:lower limit|infimum
いいかげんにしろ！
Just give it a rest!
I understand...
It's all clear now.
分かってる もう分かってんだ
A measly debris collector could work for decades
and still not be able to buy a real spaceship.
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
宇宙船なんてな―
たかだか:very high/at most/at best, デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 何十[なんじゅう]:several tens, 働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|
たかだか デブリ屋が
何十年 働いたところで―
本物[ほんもの]:genuine article/real thing/real deal, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
本物は買えやしねえってな！
What's changed,
these past three years?
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
３年で 何が変わった？
I'm still a rank and file employee
and I've got no savings.
いまだ:as yet/hitherto|not yet (with negative verb), 平[ひら, ヒラ]:something broad and flat|common|low-ranking employee, 社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 貯金[ちょきん]:putting money aside/savings|accumulated surplus of wins
俺はいまだに 平社員で貯金もない
I pick up debris
day in and day out,
デブリ:debris, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather, 毎日[まいにち]:every day
デブリを拾うだけの毎日で―
...and I still don't have the money to buy one
of these spacesuits, much less a spaceship!
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, どころ:particle used to indicate that what precedes it is an extreme example and strongly negates it, 宇宙服[うちゅうふく]:space suit, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, 金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal
マイ宇宙船どころか
この宇宙服一つ 買う金もねえ！
You'll figure it out
soon enough, too.
お前も そのうち分かるよ
Even if you say you're gonna
make your dreams come true,
夢[ゆめ]:dream, かなえる:to grant (request, wish)/to answer (prayer)|to fulfill (conditions), たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
夢をかなえるって言ったってな―
...there's some things you can do
and some things you can't!
ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
できることと
できないことがあるんだよ！
GO-S27, this is Bay Control.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), ディー:D/d, コントロール:control
（クルー）GOS-27
こちら ディーコントロール
Movement of gantry frame
to final position complete.
フレーム:frame, 定[さだ]:certainly/truly, 位置[いち]:place/situation/position, 誘導[ゆうどう]:guidance/leading/induction, 完了[かんりょう]:completion/conclusion|perfect (tense, form, aspect), 完了[ワンラ]:end/completion
ガントリーフレーム
定位置への誘導を完了
Exposure confirmed.
（機長）どうだ？
Status?
Sir. Units A, B, and C,
systems go.
ユニット:unit
はい ユニットＡＢＣ システムゴー
発進[はっしん]:departure/takeoff
いつでも発進できます
We can launch
at any time.
Are you feeling nervous?
緊張[きんちょう]:tension/mental strain/nervousness
緊張しているか？
Yes, sir.
はい
That's good. Your cargo this time
is human beings.
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 荷物[にもつ]:luggage|burden|payload (of a packet, cell, etc.)
それでいい 今度の荷物は人間だ
It's a grave responsibility.
Be as nervous as you can.
責任[せきにん]:duty/responsibility (incl. supervision of staff)|liability, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, 思い切り[おもいきり, おもいっきり]:with all one's strength/with all one's heart/resignation, 緊張[きんちょう]:tension/mental strain/nervousness
責任は大きいぞ
思い切り緊張してやれ
Yes, sir.
はい
Hachimaki, make your approach on the satellite
from the direction of the damaged dish.
ハチマキ:headband, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite, 近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with
（フィー）
ハチマキ 衛星に近づくのは―
ダメージ:damage, パラボラ:parabola, 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
ダメージのある
パラボラの方向からお願いね
It looks like its control systems
are half dead.
制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking, 計[けい]:plan|meter|(in) total, 計[はか]:progress, 半分[はんぶん]:half, 半分[はんぷん]:half minute, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
制御計が
半分 死んでるみたいだから
I know. I'm the one
who smashed the thing.
ぶっ壊す[ぶっこわす]:to destroy/to crush|to spoil
（ハチマキ）
ああ 俺がぶっ壊したからな
If you know about it, then I'll
leave the cleaning to you.
掃除[そうじ]:cleaning/sweeping/dusting, よろしく:well/properly|best regards
（フィー）
分かってんなら お掃除よろしく
I copy.
コピー:copy/photocopy
（ハチマキ）アイ コピー
Senpai, about
this debris...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, デブリ:debris
先輩 このデブリのこと…
Yeah, I know
all about it.
ああ よーく知ってるさ
Man, nothing has changed
these past three years.
ほんと:truth/reality|proper, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
ほんと
３年前と何も変わっちゃいねえ
Neither one of us...
お前も俺も…
Huh? Did you
say something?
（タナベ）えっ 何ですか？
C'mon, let's get rid
of this damn thing.
とっとと:quickly/at once/right away, 片づける[かたづける]:to tidy up|to settle (problem)|to finish||
とっとと 片づけるぞ
Oh. Right.
（タナベ）あっ はい
Listen, I'll do the basic work.
You just stay out of the way.
基本[きほん]:foundation/basis/standard, 作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing
（ハチマキ）いいか
基本作業は俺がやるから―
余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly
お前は 余計なことはしなくていい
You copy?
コピー:copy/photocopy
ユー コピー？
Huh? I copy.
コピー:copy/photocopy
（タナベ）アイ… アイ コピー
Plus, we're dealing with debris
that has moving parts this mission.
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, ミッション:mission, 動き[うごき]:movement/move|trend, デブリ:debris
それから 今回のミッションは
動きのあるデブリだ
If you don't wanna get killed by having your
face smashed in, don't open your face guard.
顔をつぶす[かおをつぶす]:to make somebody lose face/to embarrass someone/to make someone look foolish, フェイス:face, ガード:guard, 開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
顔をつぶされて死にたくないなら
フェイスガードを開けるなよ
コピー:copy/photocopy
アイ コピー
I copy...
モニター:(computer) monitor, 画面[がめん]:terminal screen/scene/picture, 画面[えづら]:the impression given by a painting or image, 苦手[にがて]:poor (at)/weak (in)|dislike (of)
（タナベ）
私 モニター画面 苦手なんですよ
I can't handle watching things
on a monitor screen...
I'm terrible at games
and stuff...
ゲーム:game, 全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
ゲームとか 全然 駄目なんで
制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking, パネル:panel, 抑える[おさえる]:to pin something down|to seize|to gain control of something|
（ハチマキ）
俺が制御パネルを抑えるまで―
You stay put over there until
I turn off the control panel.
お前は そこにいろ
Huh? Give me
a minute!
くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（タナベ）
えっ ちょっと待ってください
Watch out for
the arm.
アーム:arm, 気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care
（ハチマキ）アームに気をつけろよ
アーム:arm
（タナベ）アーム？
Arm?
（タナベ）
えっ あっ… ちょっと
H-Hey!
Watch it!
危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||
危ない うわあっ！
接触[せっしょく]:touch/contact, 警報[けいほう]:alarm/warning
（ハチマキ）ああっ… 接触警報？
Collision alert?
Crap, she did the
same damn thing I did...
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation), 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
ったく…
俺と同じようなこと やりやがって
Um... Did I do
something wrong?
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
（タナベ）あ… あの…
何か私 マズかったでしょうか？
Damn it,
that stupid rookie...!
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
（ハチマキ）くそ 新入りが
Okay, automatic controls
are cut!
自動制御[じどうせいぎょ]:automatic control, カット:cut/cutting
よし 自動制御はカット
Hachi, can you bring it back on manual?
You're pretty far out of your predicted orbit.
手動[しゅどう]:manual (operation), 戻す[もどす]:to put back|to vomit|to recover (of a market price), 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, かなり:considerably/fairly/quite, ずれる:to slide/to slip off/to get dislocated
ハチ 手動で戻せる？
予定軌道から かなりずれてるけど
Yeah, there's propellant left
in the other engine, so I...
片[かた]:one (of a pair)|incomplete|few||, 片[へん]:piece/chip/flake, エンジン:engine
（ハチマキ）
ああ もう片っぽのエンジンは―
推進剤[すいしんざい]:propellant, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
推進剤が残ってるから…
おかしい:funny/amusing|strange, 反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response
お… おかしいな
スラッサーが反応しねえ
That's weird...
The thruster's not responding.
It's not? Okay, we'll postpone
the mission and...
ミッション:mission, 延期[えんき]:postponement/adjournment
そうか
じゃあ ミッションを延期して
せっかく:stone burial chamber, せっかく:with trouble/at great pains|rare, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
（ハチマキ）
待てよ せっかく捕まえたんだ
Hold it! We finally caught this thing, so I'll
use the Fishbone to try to decelerate it.
フィッシュ:fish, ボーン:born, 減速[げんそく]:deceleration
フィッシュボーンを使って
減速させてみる
In the meantime, I'll go
check out the thruster.
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, スラスター:thruster (e.g. on a satellite), 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
その間に俺は
スラスターを確認しておくから
Understood. Careful, you'll run out
of wire in another 20 seconds.
秒[びょう]:second (60th min), ワイヤー:wire, 伸びる[のびる]:to stretch|to make progress|to grow stale (soba)||
（フィー）分かった あと20秒で
ワイヤーが伸びきるからね
コピー:copy/photocopy
（ハチマキ）アイ コピー
I copy.
Tanabe, I'm sending Yuri out to you,
so stay put where you are.
向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards
（フィー）タナベ
ユーリを向かわせるから―
そのまま:without change/as it is|just like
そのまま そこにいて
（タナベ）はい
Yes, ma'am.
Brace for impact.
衝撃[しょうげき]:shock/impact/crash, 備える[そなえる]:to furnish|to have ready|to possess (all that is needed)|
衝撃に備えて
Ten.
10 ９ ８ ７ ６
Nine.
Eight.
Seven.
Six.
Five.
５ ４ ３ ２ １ ０
Four.
Three.
Two.
One.
Zero.
Okay, Hachimaki.
How's the thruster look?
ハチマキ:headband, スラスター:thruster (e.g. on a satellite)
（フィー）ＯＫ ハチマキ
スラスターのほうはどう？
Crap, the antenna dish film is tangled up in it.
This is gonna take a while.
パラボラ:parabola, フィルム:film, 巻きつく[まきつく]:to twine around
（ハチマキ）くそ パラボラの
フィルムが巻きついてて―
かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang
ちょっと 時間かかりそうだな
Yuri, see to
recovering Tanabe.
回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
ユーリ
タナベの回収 頼んだわね
I copy.
コピー:copy/photocopy
（ユーリ）アイ コピー
Fee, I think I can get the
thruster straightened out.
フィー:phi, スラスター:thruster (e.g. on a satellite)
（ハチマキ）フィー
スラスターは なんとかなりそうだ
Okay. That's good.
（フィー）そう よかったわ
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
（ハチマキ）うわああーっ
What's wrong, Hachi?!
（フィー）どうしたの？ ハチ
（ハチマキ）うわあっ
（フィー）ハチ！
Hachi!
（ハチマキ）あっ ああっ…
I got hit by the wire,
but I'm okay.
ワイヤー:wire, 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
ワイヤーにやられたけど
大丈夫 機能は生きてる
My suit's
still functional.
I'm sorry, I didn't catch it
on the monitor.
モニター:(computer) monitor
（フィー）
ごめん モニターできてなかった
There doesn't seem to be much
secondary debris, though.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, デブリ:debris, わずか:only/merely/(a) little, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
でも ２次デブリはわずかみたい
That last impact changed
your vector again, so...
ベクトル:vector, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
今ので ベクトルが
また変わったから あっ…
Oh, no...
This orbit is...
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track
マズい この軌道は…
GO-S27, do you read?
This is Control Section.
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
（クレア）
GOS-27 聞こえますか？
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
こちら 管制課です
There is a risk of a near miss with debris
DBR-072-1414 on your flight path.
デブリ:debris
デブリ DBR 0721414と―
進路[しんろ]:route/course|one's future course (e.g. after graduating high school), ニアミス:near-miss, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 発生[はっせい]:outbreak|generation (e.g. of power or heat)|ontogeny
進路上にて
ニアミスする危険が発生
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（船長）ん？
（操縦士）何やってんだ？ 半課は
What's Half Section
think they're doing?
What about
an orbit change?
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 変更[へんこう]:change/modification/alteration
軌道変更を
Is there time? It's coming straight at us,
so our relative velocity is too high.
間に合う[まにあう]:to be in time for|to serve (suit, meet) the purpose/to be good enough
間に合うか？
逆行[ぎゃっこう, ぎゃくこう]:reverse movement/retrogression|retrogradation, 相対[あいたい]:confrontation/facing/between ourselves, 相対[そうたい]:relativity|relative, 速度[そくど]:speed/velocity/rate, 速い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
逆行で来ているから
相対速度が速すぎる
Deploy debris bumper!
デブリ:debris
デブリバンパを出せ
はい
Yes, sir!
This is the
pilot speaking.
機長[きちょう]:captain (of an aircraft), 案内[あんない]:information/guidance|to guide, 申し上げる[もうしあげる]:to say/to tell|to do
（機長）
機長より ご案内 申し上げます
We will begin immediate
anti-impact preparations...
当[とう]:this (business organisation or place), 当[はた]:or|furthermore|perhaps||, 機[はた]:loom, 機[き]:chance|machine|aircraft||, ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently, 大気圏[たいきけん]:the atmosphere, 突入[とつにゅう]:rushing into/breaking into|plunging into (war, etc.), 向ける[むける]:to turn towards/to point
当機は ただいまより
大気圏突入に向け―
...to ensure our safety
during atmospheric reentry.
安全[あんぜん]:safety|security, 確保[かくほ]:guarantee/maintain/ensure, 対[たい]:opposite|versus|to (e.g. "winning a game five to three")||, 対[つい]:pair|antithesis|counter for items that come in pairs|, 衝撃[しょうげき]:shock/impact/crash, 態勢[たいせい]:attitude/posture/preparedness
安全を確保するため
対衝撃態勢に入ります
Hachi, get back here ASAP!
You're in the shuttle's orbit!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（フィー）ハチ 早く戻って！
シャトル:shuttlecock, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 侵入[しんにゅう]:invasion/incursion/raid
シャトル軌道に侵入してる
Hey, wait a minute...!
I know that shuttle!
シャトル:shuttlecock
（ハチマキ）
ちょっと待てよ このシャトルは…
That's the one that
Cheng-Shin's on!
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
チェンシンが乗ってるやつだ！
Senpai! Get out of there, Senpai!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（タナベ）
先輩 逃げてください！ 先輩
Losing the mass of one person might...
質量[しつりょう]:mass
人間１人分の質量なら…
- Shut up!
シャトル:shuttlecock
（ハチマキ）うるせえ！
だったら シャトルはどうなる？
If I left, what would
happen to the shuttle?!
はっ…
This is one time when running away
or failing isn't an option!
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, ばかり:only/merely|approximately, 逃げ[にげ]:escape/getaway/evasion, 負け[まけ]:defeat/loss/losing (a game), 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
（ハチマキ）今回ばかりは
逃げも負けも許されねえ
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
許されねえんだよ！
It ain't an option!
But senpai!
The shuttle has bumpers!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, シャトル:shuttlecock, バンパー:bumper
（タナベ）
でも先輩 シャトルにはバンパーが
There's no way that it can protect it
from something this big!
サイズ:size, 防ぐ[ふせぐ]:to defend against/to protect against|to prevent, きれる:to break/to snap|to be injured, きれる:to be able to wear/to fit into
（ハチマキ）このサイズを
防ぎきれるわけねえだろ！
Hachi...
ハチ
Damn it, I haven't even gotten
my spaceship yet...
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation), 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure
（ハチマキ）ったく… 宇宙船も
まだ手に入れてないってのに
Yuri-san, senpai is gonna...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）ユーリさん 先輩は？
All we can do now is have faith
in Hoshino-san's abilities.
技術[ぎじゅつ]:technology|technique|art, 信じる[しんじる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in
（ユーリ）あとは星野さんの技術を
信じるしかありません
GO-S27, this is Entry Approach.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is)
（管制官）GOS-27 こちら
リエントリアプローチ
It's no use! Even if we accelerate,
there's not enough time to raise our orbit!
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 加速[かそく]:acceleration/speeding up, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 上げる[あげる]:to raise|to do up (one's hair)|to fly (a kite, etc.)||, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
（機長）駄目だ！ 加速して
軌道を上げる時間が足りない！
We have confirmed a red alert.
Abort reentry corridor.
LTS auto functions
are totally dead...
オート:auto/automobile/automatic, 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty, 完全[かんぜん]:perfection/completeness
（ハチマキ）
オート機能は完全に死んでる
So I'll have to do it
by hand, then!
やっぱ:too/also|still, 手動[しゅどう]:manual (operation)
やっぱ 手動でやるしかねえ
Okay, this one's
still online...
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
よし こいつは生きてる
Fee! Give me a realtime feed of the course
data for the shuttle and the debris!
フィー:phi, シャトル:shuttlecock, デブリ:debris, 進路[しんろ]:route/course|one's future course (e.g. after graduating high school), データ:data/datum
（ハチマキ）フィー シャトルと
デブリの進路データを―
リアルタイム:real time, 送る[おくる]:to send (a thing)|to take or escort (a person somewhere)|to bid farewell (to the departed)||
リアルタイムで
こっちに送ってくれ
（フィー）分かった
Got it.
Here goes...
（ハチマキ）さて…
Judging from this remaining propellant,
I've only got one chance.
残り[のこり]:remnant/residue/remaining, 推進剤[すいしんざい]:propellant, ワンチャンス:one chance/only opportunity
（ハチマキ）残りの
推進剤からするとワンチャンス
And I have to thrust through the center
of mass of a spinning body, or it's all over.
しかも:moreover/furthermore|nevertheless, 回る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|, 回る[まわる]:to turn|to visit several places|to function well|, 中心[ちゅうしん]:center/centre|-centered, 中心[なかご]:core|tang (of a sword, etc.)|middle of a nest of boxes, 射抜く[いぬく]:to shoot through something (wall, body, etc.)/to pierce (e.g. with an arrow or a look), アウト:out
しかも 回ってるやつの
中心を射抜けなきゃアウトだ
Can I seriously
pull this off...?
やれるかな
マジで
ハァ ハァ ハァ…
Can I really
do this...?
（ハチマキ）できるのか？ 本当に
Stay focused...
迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|, こらえる:to bear/to stand|to restrain
迷うな まだだ こらえろ
Not yet.
Stay with it...
Just a little more, and its position
will be along the center of gravity...
位置[いち]:place/situation/position, 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 中心[ちゅうしん]:center/centre|-centered, 中心[なかご]:core|tang (of a sword, etc.)|middle of a nest of boxes
こいつの位置は もう少しで中心
Those Half Section guys
did that?
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe
（機長）
半課の連中がやったのか
加速[かそく]:acceleration/speeding up, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track
加速して こっちの軌道の上に
It accelerated and moved
into an orbit above ours!
ああ…
（ハチマキ）
フッ フフ ハハハハッ…
Well, I'll be! I actually did it!
何だよ できたじゃないか
See that, Cheng-Shin?
なっ チェンシン
Hoshino-san!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（ユーリ）星野さん
（タナベ）先輩
Senpai!
（ハチマキ）あっ…
Are you all right?
（タナベ）大丈夫でしたか？
Oops. Darn it...
いっけ:a house/a home/a family, いっけ:prefix used to strengthen a derogatory adjective
…と いっけない
うう うわっ うわあっ…
Hey, rookie, don't be
in such a rush.
おいおい:Hey!/Wait a minute!|boohoo, おいおい:gradually/by degrees/little by little, 焦る[あせる]:to be in a hurry/to be impatient/to be flustered, 新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
（ハチマキ）おいおい
そんなに焦んなよ 新入り
えっ
Sir?
You're just getting started.
まだまだ:still some way to go before the goal/still more to come/much more, 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from), ばっかり:only/merely|approximately, 焦る[あせる]:to be in a hurry/to be impatient/to be flustered
まだまだ 始まったばっかりだ
焦んなくていい
There's no rush. Just take your time
and build it up a little at a time.
ゆっくり:slowly/at ease/restful, 積み上げる[つみあげる]:to pile up/to make a heap|to acquire (e.g. experience)
ゆっくり ゆっくり
積み上げていけばいいって
Am I right?
だろ？
（タナベ）えっ まあ…
Huh? I guess...
Give it three years. Nah, make it five,
and I'll have you whipped into shape.
一人前になる[いちにんまえになる]:to come of age/to become an adult/to become fully qualified
（ハチマキ）３年… いや
５年もすりゃあ 一人前になるって
Five years, huh...?
（タナベ）５年ですか…
Wait, you didn't see my breathtaking
EVA work, did you? Make it ten!
華麗[かれい]:splendid/magnificent/gorgeous, 損なう[そこなう]:to harm/to hurt|to fail to ...
（ハチマキ）あっ お前
俺の華麗なＥＶＡを見損なったな？
こりゃ:hey there/I say/see here
10年だ こりゃ
It just keeps climbing,
doesn't it?
いきなり:abruptly/suddenly/all of a sudden, 増える[ふえる]:to increase/to multiply
（タナベ）いきなり増えてますね
Um... Who's going to write up
the letter of apology for this one?
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 始末書[しまつしょ]:written explanation or apology, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
（ユーリ）あの… 今回の始末書
誰が書くんでしょうか？
♪～
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
Return Trajectory
This is our tuition plan. It's a bargain.
女性[じょせい, にょしょう]:woman/female|feminine gender, 我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company, 学費[がくひ]:tuition/school expenses, プラン:plan, 得[とく]:profit/advantage|rebirth in paradise, entering nirvana, 得[う]:to get/to acquire|to be possible
（女性１）我が社の
学費プラン お得ですよ
（課長）なんか
入っちゃうんだよねえ
You get dragged in,
don't you?
そ… それって
T-That's a...
It doesn't matter
what I write.
いいんだよ 何だって
えっ…
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
俺たちの仕事は デブリを
回収するだけだしさ
Our job is to collect debris,
end of story.
My father was a astronaut
through and through.
女性[じょせい, にょしょう]:woman/female|feminine gender, 純粋[じゅんすい]:pure/true/genuine, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
（女性２）父は
純粋な宇宙飛行士でした
You can't do that!
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
駄目ですよ そんなの
Damn it, girl,
answer me!
返事[へんじ]:reply/answer/response, ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
返事ぐらい
しろってんだよ！
Hey!
（ハチマキ）こら！
He should go home
to Earth!
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（タナベ）
地球に戻るべきなんです
I'd leave them love!
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
愛です！
（ハチマキ）お前 バカだ
You're an idiot.